<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC 
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='irkerd.8'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>irkerd</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>Aug 27 2012</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>irker</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='product'>irker</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Commands</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>irkerd</refname>
<refpurpose>relay for shipping notifications to IRC servers</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>irkerd</command>
     <arg>-d <replaceable>debuglevel</replaceable></arg>
     <arg>-l <replaceable>logfile</replaceable></arg>
     <arg>-n <replaceable>nick</replaceable></arg>
     <arg>-p <replaceable>password</replaceable></arg>
     <arg>-V</arg>
	 <arg>-h</arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para><application>irkerd</application> is a specialized write-only IRC
client intended to be used for shipping notification messages to IRC
channels. The use case in mind when it was designed was broadcasting
notifications from commit hooks in version-control systems.</para>

<para>The main advantage of relaying through this daemon over
individual scripted sends from applications is that it can maintain
connection state for multiple channels, rather than producing obnoxious
join/leave channel spam on every message.</para>

<para><application>irkerd</application> is a socket server that
listens on for UDP or TCP packets on port 6659 for textual request
lines containing JSON objects and terminated by a newline. Each JSON
object must have two members: "to" specifying a destination or
destination list, and "privmsg" specifying the message text.
Examples:

<programlisting>
{"to":"irc://chat.freenode.net/git-ciabot", "privmsg":"Hello, world!"}
{"to":["irc://chat.freenode.net/#git-ciabot","irc://chat.freenode.net/#gpsd"],"privmsg":"Multichannel test"}
{"to":"irc://chat.hypothetical.net:6668/git-ciabot", "privmsg":"Hello, world!"}
{"to":"irc://chat.hypothetical.net:6668/git-private?key=topsecret", "privmsg":"Keyed channel test"}
</programlisting></para>

<para>If the channel part of the URL does not have one of the prefix
characters <quote>#</quote>, <quote>&amp;</quote>, or
<quote>+</quote>, a <quote>#</quote> will be prepended to it before
shipping - <emphasis>unless</emphasis>the channel part has the suffix
",isnick" (which is unconditionally removed).</para>

<para>The host part of the URL may have a port-number suffix separated by a
colon, as shown in the third example; otherwise
<application>irkerd</application> sends messages to the the default 6667 IRC
port of each server.</para>

<para>To join password-protected (mode +k) channels, the channel part of the
URL may be followed with a query-string indicating the channel key, of the
form <quote>?secret</quote> or <quote>?key=secret</quote>, where
<quote>secret</quote> is the channel key.</para>

<para>An empty message is legal and will cause
<application>irkerd</application> to join the target channels without
actually emitting a message.  This may be useful for advertising that
an instance is up and running, or for joining a channel to log its
traffic.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='options'><title>OPTIONS</title>

<para><application>irkerd</application> takes the following options:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>-d</term>
<listitem><para>Takes a following value, setting the debugging level from
it. This option will generally only be of interest to developers;
consult the source code for details.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>-l</term>
<listitem><para>Takes a following filename, logs traffic to that file.
Each log line consists of three |-separated fields; a numeric
timestamp in Unix time, the FQDN of the sending server, and the
message data.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>-n</term>
<listitem><para>Takes a following value, setting the nick
to be used. If the nick contains a numeric format element
(such as %03d) it is used to generate suffixed fallback names
in the event of a nick collision.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>-p</term>
<listitem><para>Takes a following value, setting a nickserv
password to be used. If given, this password is shipped to
authenticate the nick on receipt of a welcome message.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>-V</term>
<listitem><para>Write the program version to stdout and
terminate.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>-h</term>
<listitem><para>Print usage instructions and terminate.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='limitations'><title>LIMITATIONS</title>
<para>Requests via UDP optimizes for lowest latency and network load
by avoiding TCP connection setup time; the cost is that delivery is
not reliable in the face of packet loss.</para>

<para>An <application>irkerd</application> instance with a
publicly-accessible request socket could complicate blocking of IRC
spam by making it easy for spammers to submit while hiding their IP
addresses; the better way to deploy, then, is on places like
project-hosting sites where the <application>irkerd</application>
socket can be visible from commit-hook code but not exposed to the
outside world. Priming your firewall with blocklists of IP addresses
known to spew spam is always a good idea.</para>

<para>The absence of any option to set the service port is deliberate.
If you think you need to do that, you have a problem better solved at
your firewall.</para>

<para>IRC has a message length limit of 510 bytes; generate your
privmsg attribute values with appropriate care.</para>

<para>IRC ignores any text after an embedded newline. Be aware that
<application>irkerd</application> will turn payload strings with
embedded newlines into multiple IRC sends to avoid having message data
discarded. </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>irkerhook</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='authors'><title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@snark.thyrsus.com</email>.  See the
project page at <ulink
url='http://www.catb.org/~esr/irker'>http://www.catb.org/~esr/irker</ulink>
for updates and other resources, including an installable repository
hook script.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

